Okay,
בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, good to be back. Today's דף daf is
ל״ד. Lamed Dalet. We pick up from six lines from the bottom
of ל״ג עמוד ב׳, Lamed Gimmel Amud Bet, גופא, Gufa, end of
the line. Okay, so we've been discussing, we've been getting on a
bit of a digression here because the issue has been the whole
question about the payment of תרומה Trumah and whether the payment of
תרומה Trumah is fundamentally a question about the amount of value that
was destroyed, דמים, Damim, or is it basically a replacement of the
fruit, מידה, Mida, which relates to the issue about if it's worthless
like חמץ בפסח, Chametz b'Pesach, do you return it? But that leads
the גמרא Gemara into a number of digressions,
and one was actually seeing a debate—well, this wasn't a digression, but
seeing a debate of the תנאים Tannaim about this issue,
about—well, no, excuse me, about what seemed to be a parallel issue
about whether it's defined by כזית Kezayis or a פרוטה Pruta when
the payment actually kicks in, which would seem to be directly related.
And then the גמרא Gemara from there turns to the issue about—about
that if you don't actually—you can't actually be מפריש Mafrish תרומה, Trumah,
this is just quickly reviewing the last two days because it's a
lot of issues—you can't actually be מפריש Mafrish תרומה Trumah by חמץ
Chametz because you can't be מפריש Mafrish תרומה Trumah that's אסור בהנאה,
assur b'hana'ah, that doesn't give the כהן Kohen anything—anything serious, or that
doesn't make the remainder any better. And now we're turning to the
issue about is it possible to actually take טמא Tamei grapes and
press them in a way in which the juice that comes out
is not טמא. Tamei. Now that doesn't seem directly relevant, but it
is relevant because—because in the discussion back and forth of can you
give—are you חייב chayav for תרומה Trumah that has no value, the
issue came up about טמא—about, Tamei you know, about תרומה Trumah that's
טמא, Tamei, what can you use it for? And the question is,
well, why is that an issue? Why can't you just press the
grapes if you have טמא Tamei grapes in a way that the
juice doesn't become טמא? Tamei? So that leads—so that issue about does
it have value, do you go by the value, do you go
by the amount, do you go by replacing the fruit, do you
go by the value, let us into this issue, an example of
טמא Tamei grapes, which raised the question of why can't you get
the juice out without making them טמא? Tamei? Okay, so let's take—and
let's take a look. And then the—and then the גמרא Gemara wanted
to—and then the גמרא's Gemara answer, at least one answer was maybe
you can, but we're afraid that in the process you'll come to
eat the grapes, אתי לידי תקלה. assi lidei takala. So that's where
we are right now. There might be an acceptable way to extract
the juice or to make use of the thing without actually it
becoming טמא, Tamei, but we won't allow that because you'll come to
actually eat the טמא Tamei grapes. So let's take a look now.
גופא, Gufa, six lines from the bottom of ל״ג עמוד ב׳. Lamed
Gimmel Amud Bet. גמרא Gemara says like this: מדליקין בפת ובשמן של
תרומה שנטמאת. Madlikin b'pas u'b'shemen shel trumah she'nitmeit. If you have—this is
the normal thing of what you do with תרומה טמאה. trumah tmeiah.
You have טמא Tamei bread or טמא Tamei oil, you use it
for firewood. That's what you do with—a כהן Kohen is allowed to
do with תרומה טמאה, trumah tmeiah, he is allowed to destroy it
and get the benefit from it as it's being destroyed. Okay. So
אביי אמר משמיה דחזקיה ורבא אמר דבי רב יצחק בר מרתא. Abaye
amar mishmei d'Chizkiyah v'Rava amar d'bei Rav Yitzchak bar Marta. So both
אביי Abaye and רבא Rava say from different traditions, אמר רב הונא:
amar Rav Huna: לא שנו אלא פת. lo shanu ela pat.
That only by bread.
But, as we're about to see, as soon as you throw it
into the fire, you won't come to eat from it. Because now
we've introduced this idea that there's this problem about destroying תרומה Trumah
or processing תרומה טמאה, trumah tmeiah, you might come to eat from
it. So why isn't that an issue here? So they said: Alright,
that's by bread. And we said before that and before we said
by oil, you can put oil in a disgusting vessel that nobody
would want to eat from it after. אבל חיטי, aval chiti, but
if you're talking about—about—about grain,
then like wheat kernels, then לא, lo, you can't use it. שמא
יבוא לידי תקלה, shema yavo lidei takala, like exactly לידי תקלה, lidei
takala, exactly what we said before, the same way you can't press
grapes, טמא Tamei grapes, even if you could do it in a
way that the juice would not be טמא, Tamei, we won't let
you do it because you'll come to eat it. Here too, if
in the process of destroying it, the thing will not become disgusting
and you—you might come to eat from it, we won't allow you
to do it. ורבי יוחנן אמר, v'Rabbi Yochanan amar, now ורבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says, אפילו חיטי, afilu chiti, even by grapes. ואמאי, v'amai,
why does he allow that? ניחוש דדילמא אתי בהן לידי תקלה, neichosh
d'dilma ati b'hain lidei takala, let's be afraid you might come to
eat from it. Now maybe he doesn't hold that principle. That's only
one answer before, but the גמרא's Gemara now assuming that that's a
principle. So כדאמר רב אסי, k'd'amar Rav Assi, like רב אסי Rav
Assi says, top of ל״ד, Lamed Dalet, בשליקתא ומיאסתא, b'shlikta u'mista,
we're talking about like boiled and therefore like disgusting grain. Grain that—that
basically because they're boiled and it's soft, as soon as you throw
it into the fire, it'll become disgusting. So it's just like the
bread. We're talking about a circumstance in which you will not come
to eat from it once you start the process of destroying
it. But אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, if it was hard...
And it wouldn't be disgusting, yes, he would agree that that would
be a problem.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is the one who said ענבים שנטמאו בראשותן
anavim shenitma'u beroshotan and this whole discussion. דרוך בהאי גיסא ובהאי גיסא
daruch behai gisa ubehai gisa and it would be כשר kasher for
נסכים, nesachim, right?
So it's not disgusting because he was making grape juice out of
it or, you know, and what about the תקלה? takala? Maybe he'll
come to eat from the grapes? Maybe that wine, grapes you're going
to make into wine is different and you're not going to come
to eat from the grapes?
No, no, no, when רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, that's the exact
point of the גמרא Gemara before, when רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said
you could do little by little, he was talking that it was,
that it was not תרומה. terumah. That you could take normally, normally
טמא tamei grapes and make wine, and then make the wine, use
the wine for נסכים, nesachim, the wine would not be טמא. tamei.
But the גמרא Gemara is saying, so why don't you do that
in a תרומה terumah scenario? Says no, in a תרומה terumah scenario,
once the grapes become טמא, tamei, I'm not going to let you
do this process because you'll come to eat from the grapes. That's
a whole different, what I said was a way if you just
had a normal case of טומאה tumah to get the juice not
טמא. tamei. But I, but you can't use this idea for תרומה
terumah because of אתי לידי תקלה, atsi lidei takala, which is exactly
what the גמרא Gemara now is dealing with is that answer. Okay.
Now, the גמרא Gemara says like this. הכא נמי בשליקתא דמיאסתא. hacha
nami beshlikta d'mistai. והיכא איתמר דרב אשי? veheicha itmar d'Rav Ashi? Where
was רב אשי Rav Ashi stated this when he used this as
a תירוץ, teretz, that the thing was already cooked and therefore it
would be disgusting and you don't have to worry about this problem?
אהא דאמר רב אבין בר אבא הכא אמר רב יצחק אבא, ahada
amar Rav Avin bar Abba hacha amar Rav Yitzchak Abba,
that which רב אבין בר רב אחא Rav Avin bar Rav Acha
says in the
name of רב יצחק אבא, Rav Yitzchak Abba, אמר רב יצחק קמא,
amar Rav Yitzchak kama, אבא שאול גבל שבבית רבי היה. Abba Shaul
gaval shebe-beit rebbi haya.
אבא שאול Abba Shaul was the like the, the dough maker, the
kneader, with a K, of רבי's Rebbi household. והיו מחממין לו חמים,
vahayuh mechamim lo chamim,
and they would heat up for him the hot water for his
baking בחיבזין של תרומה טמאה, bechivzin shel terumah tmeiah,
with the grain of תרומה טמאה. terumah tmeiah. רש"י Rashi says, you
know, תרומה טמאה terumah tmeiah goes at a, it's very, there's a
very low market price for that because who wants תרומה טמאה? terumah
tmeiah? So they would buy it up and use it for firewood,
because you're allowed to burn תרומה טמאה. terumah tmeiah. That's what you
do with תרומה טמאה. terumah tmeiah.
And they would use it to make, to make dough. Now the
only thing is, is that רבי Rebbi would be, now רש"י Rashi
says part of the חידוש chidush is that רבי Rebbi would be
אוכל חולין בטהרה. ochel chullin betaharah. And so part of the חידוש
chidush is that he's not afraid, you know, you're using this as
the firewood and then you're having your water and your pot above
it and you're drawing from that water to make the dough, but
anyway we're not afraid that in the process you'll come to actually
touch some of the grain down there that's טמא. tamei. So that's
part of the חידוש. chidush. But the גמרא's Gemara question is, why
could you do this anyway? ללוש בה עיסה בטהרה, lalush bein issah
betaharah, so he would use this to make dough בטהרה betaharah and
wouldn't be concerned that you'd come in contact. But okay, that's all
very nice that he wouldn't be concerned about that, but אמאי, amai,
why are you allowed to do this? ניחוש שמא יבא לידי תקלה,
neichosh shema yavo lidei takala, maybe if you're throwing this grain down
on the fire to use as firewood, you'll pop some in your
mouth? So אמר רב אשי בשליקתא דמיאסתא, amar Rav Ashi beshlikta d'mistai,
it's already cooked, boiled, and therefore it's disgusting when you throw it
down and therefore we're not afraid that in the process you'll come
to, it'll come to the problem what?
It's already cooked and boiled it, it doesn't seem
to be too good for firewood. Yeah, I don't know the answer
to that. That's a good question. It's so long after.
Right, he's not making a historical claim, he's speculating this will be
a way to answer this question. Maybe they
were wealthy and didn't
have to, well right, that's a general question why do you have
to buy the cheap firewood anyway? Yeah, I don't know. It is
true, Michael also asks a good question. You know, look, the גמרא
Gemara before, you don't have to say that we buy into this
idea of שמא יבא לידי תקלה, shema yavo lidei takala, it was
an answer according to one approach, you know, but now the גמרא's
Gemara working with the assumption that everybody buys into it. I will
also say that תוספות Tosafos points out that based on other גמרות
Gemaros that when you burn תרומה טמאה, terumah tmeiah, it seems from
other גמרות Gemaros that only כהנים Kohanim are allowed to benefit from
it. The same way only כהנים Kohanim can benefit from the eating
of תרומה. terumah. So רש"י Rashi doesn't seem to take that approach,
but תוספות Tosafos does. And תוספות Tosafos therefore says, so maybe we'll
have to assume that he was doing it like for the benefit
of כהנים, Kohanim, that כהנים, Kohanim, not that כהנים Kohanim have to
do the act of burning it, but that the כהנים Kohanim have
to benefit from it. So that maybe the כהנים Kohanim were eating
from this bread. So it'd be even funnier. רבי Rebbi is buying
תרומה טמאה terumah tmeiah to make bread in his household to feed
the כהנים Kohanim in his household. I mean, okay, like it seems
like a lot of effort. Anyway, all right. Now the גמרא Gemara
continues.
אביי בר אבין ורב חנינא בר אבין, Abaye bar Avin and Rav
Chanina bar Avin, so אביי בר אבין Abaye bar Avin and רב
חנינא בר אבין, Rav Chanina bar Avin, apparently two brothers, תנו תרומות
בי רבא, tanu Terumos bei Rava, they were learning תרומות Terumos in
the house of רבא. Rava. All right, that was the מסכת masecheth
for the year or for the month. פגע בהו רבא בר מתנה,
paga behu Rava bar Masnah, so רבא בר מתנה Rava bar Masnah
bumped into them. אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to them, oh
you guys are learning, you guys are learning
תרומות? Terumos? מאי אמריתו בתרומות, mai amritu beTerumos, tell me some חידושים
chidushim you said when you were learning תרומות Terumos דבי מר debei
Mar when you were learning it in the house of the master,
of רבא's Rava house.
אמרו ליה, amru lei, they said to him, ומאי קשיא לך, umai
kashya lach, you know why, what's bothering you about it? Like obviously
if you're asking us, it's not סתם stam curiosity. Oh, tell me
a חידוש. chidush. I don't know why not. But you know presumably
you've learned this before and you've got some questions about it and
you're interested to know like what we said. Maybe it'll help you
with your issue. So what issues do you have about תרומות? Terumos?
What are your questions about תרומות? Terumos? מאי... mai... What's bothering you?
So לך, lacha, אמר להו, amar lahu, he said back to them,
תנן, Tnan, here I'll tell you something that bothers me about in
תרומות. Terumos. We taught in the משנה Mishnah in
תרומות, Terumos, שתילי תרומות שנטמאו, Shtilei Terumos she'nitme'u, plantings of תרומות Terumos
that became טמא. tamei. Basically you had something that was תרומה, Terumah,
let's say, I don't know, you know,
grain or onions or whatever it was and rather than and and
you went ahead and it became טמא. tamei. So rather than eat
the grain or the onions which anyway you can't do cause it's
טמא tamei now and rather than burn it, you know what you
did? You replanted it. So now you take your טמא תרומה tamei
Terumah grain and you plant it and you're going to grow wheat
or your טמא תרומה tamei Terumah onions and you plant it and
you're going to grow more onions. Okay so now what? So what's
the status of those things that you planted?
So ושתלן, vishatlon, you replanted them. טהורים מלטמא, Tehorim mil'tamei, they they
stop being טמא tamei because basically the idea is is that things
that are מחובר לקרקע mechubar l'karka attached to the ground are טהור.
tahor. Now that doesn't always work if you had a טמא, tamei,
I don't know, you know,
brick let's say and then you were or you know or pipe
and you attached it into a building at what stage does it
lose its further its identity? תלוש ולבסוף חברו, Talush ul'vasof chiburo, the
whole discussion. But something that is growing or that can grow and
take root and you put it in the ground and it grows
and takes root that's not just מחובר, mechubar, it's like זרוע, zarua,
it's like planted in the ground and we'll see an idea of
זריעה zri'ah in a different context coming up a little bit. That
that is now it's like part of the ground and it loses
its טומאה. tum'ah. So the first הלכה halacha is, one minute, it
is טהורים מלטמא, Tehorim mil'tamei, they are no longer טמא. tamei. But
אסורין מלאכול, asurin mil'echol,
but they remain forbidden to be eaten. Now that's a bit of
a bizarre split. The reason they couldn't be eaten was because they
were טמא, tamei, it was תרומה טמאה. Terumah t'meiah. Why do they
remain forbidden to be eaten? So that's what's bothered me, I never
understood this משנה. Mishnah. Maybe you came up with a good explanation.
Yeah, Charlie?
What if you plant them in a graveyard? Haha! Okay, that's that
was רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's thing after the cave.
Yeah, as they're growing they're still טהור, tahor, you know, whether as
soon as they get cut then they're in the graveyard and become
טמא, tamei, that's one thing, but anything that's growing is not cannot
become cannot become טמא. tamei. Well yes, but let's understand why at
least. So וכי מאחר דאיטהרו מלטמא, v'chi mei'achar d'itehuru mil'tamei, once the
planting them made them טהור, tahor, אמאי אסורין מלאכול? amai asurin mil'echol?
Why can they no longer be eaten? אמרו ליה, Amru lei, they
said to him, הכי אמר רבה, hachi amar Rabbah, oh it's a
good point, let me tell you what we learned that משנה Mishnah
and here's what רבה Rabbah said, מאי אסורין? mai asurin? אסורין, asurin,
what does it mean they're forbidden to eat?
אסורין
לזרים, asurin l'zarim, means non-כהנים Kohanim can't eat it. Okay so then
what it's basically saying is no no it is saying something, it's
saying planting it affects its טומאה tum'ah status, doesn't affect its תרומה
Terumah status. Once it becomes planted it stops being טמא tamei but
it remains תרומה. Terumah. Now you could say that's pretty obvious, I
understand that there's a concept that growing things are not טמא tamei
but there's not the same type of concept that growing things aren't
תרומה. Terumah. I mean it is true that you don't take תרומה
Terumah while it's still growing but still those are not seen as
much as contradictory ideas. But anyway he says that's what it's coming
to tell you, just that it's still תרומה. Terumah. So he said
מאי קמשמע לן, mai kamashma lan, so what is the חידוש? chiddush?
Sort of recognizing that Charlie would say 'oh but then isn't that
obvious?' No it is telling you a חידוש. chiddush. It's telling you
גידולי תרומה תרומה, gidulei Terumah Terumah,
not just that planting them doesn't change the status, it's going further
and what it's saying is is that things that grow from תרומה
Terumah are תרומה. Terumah. If I take a תרומה Terumah seed, a
a piece of grain of תרומה Terumah and I plant it in
the ground and I you know water it and plow it and
wait six months or nine months and then a whole stalk of
wheat grows. Is that wheat תרומה Terumah or is it טבל, tevel,
right? It grew from a תרומה Terumah seed. What is the status?
That's called גידולי תרומה. gidulei Terumah. So he says yes, is it
obvious that as when you plant it it remains תרומה? Terumah? That's
obvious. But what's less obvious here is if it continues to grow
is the growth or if it was a seed or whatever is
the growth תרומה? Terumah? And that's the חידוש. chiddush. The חידוש chiddush
of the משנה Mishnah is planting it will take away the טומאה
tum'ah but planting it won't take away the תרומה Terumah and not
only that even new stuff that grows will also remain תרומה. Terumah.
That's the חידוש chiddush of that משנה. Mishnah. So he says I
don't buy it.
He
says why are we worried about the דקלא dekala after that?
All right let's worry about the דקלא dekala in a minute. Let's
first finish this idea. And we'll see why the גמרא Gemara is
bringing this whole discussion in anyway. Okay so we have you know
we have to figure out what this is doing in our whole
discussion. Anyway so he says ומאי קמשמע לן גידולי תרומה תרומה, u'mai
kamashma lan gidulei Terumah Terumah, so what? It's telling me that things
that grow from תרומה Terumah are תרומה? Terumah? תנינא, Tanina, but that
we so he is it Charlie's was a question or a statement?
So what's the חידוש chiddush of that therefore he says back to
them, that things that grow from תרומה Terumah are still remain תרומה?
Terumah? We also taught that. That's also a משנה. Mishnah. גידולי תרומה
תרומה, gidulei Terumah Terumah, things that grow from תרומה Terumah are תרומה.
Terumah. וכי תימא גידולי גידולין, v'chi teima gidulei gidulin, ah,
maybe the חידוש chiddush is a second degree גידולי גידולין. gidulei gidulin.
Now what's גידולי גידולין? gidulei gidulin? So it's a מחלוקת machlokes רש"י
Rashi תוספות. Tosfos. תוספות Tosfos has probably what's the simplest read. reading
of this, which is second generation. You take a grain of תרומה,
Terumah, you plant it, the wheat stalk that grows is תרומה, Terumah,
you take the next grain, the grain from that wheat stalk and
you plant that and then the wheat stalk that grows from that
is תרומה, Terumah, that's גידולי גידולין, Gidulei Gidulin, two generations, okay. Or
רש"י Rashi says it slightly different because the גמרא Gemara says that
it would only be true, let's read the next two lines, that
maybe it's telling me even גידולי גידולין, Gidulei Gidulin, וכי תימא גידולי
גידולין, v'chi teima gidulei gidulin, ומאי
קמשמע לן, u'mai kamashmalan,
what does it tell me? בדבר שאין זרעו כלה, b'davar she'ein zar'o
kalah, in
something that the seed does not get destroyed. When you plant the
example I've been giving you of a grain of wheat, when it
grows there's no longer any seed left, right, the seed turns into
the stalk, there's nothing left. So in that case we would say,
I'll just say תוספות Tosafos way, a second generation would remain, would
be okay because you know it's so much removed from that original
seed and the original seed doesn't even exist at all. But let's
say it's something that as it grows it doesn't get destroyed, let's
say I take an onion bulb and I plant it, right? And
that grows, okay, so then and from that then you know other
bulbs come out of that and then I take one of the
other bulbs and I plant that, and then I take a second
generation from that, so there that's גידולי גידולים, gidulei gidulim, it's a
second generation but it's not like the original thing stopped existing and
therefore it's more connected to the original and we would say that
that also has a status of תרומה. Terumah. That's the way תוספות
Tosafos says it, that it's a second generation. רש"י Rashi does not
even emphasize so much a second generation. רש"י Rashi in the example
of the onion bulb says, again I'm waiting for some gardener here
to correct me because I don't know I'm just repeating what רש"י
Rashi and תוספות Tosafos say. I don't know what happens but according
to רש"י Rashi you plant an onion bulb and not only does
the bulb grow but like other bulbs sort of cluster around it,
so you know grow as well as an outgrowth of it. So
רש"י Rashi says that that is גידולי גידולין gidulei gidulin in the
sense that it's not just the other bulbs, it's not just the
growth of the original bulb but it's the actual other bulbs as
well that you know sort of grow out of that. Okay, so
some degree it's a second derivative, it's not seen as just directly
from the thing itself, whether it's a second planting or it's a
additional bulbs, but anyway we would say that in something שאין זרעו
כלה she'ein zar'o kalah where the original thing has not been destroyed
and still remains present, then even this type of a second derivative
would also remain תרומה. Terumah.
So maybe in the wheat case it wouldn't remain?
The second derivative would not be, okay, so maybe that's the חידוש,
chiddush, one minute, maybe
so he says look you can't tell me that's the point here,
we know that, ah maybe the point is a second derivative is
תרומה. Terumah. So he says וכי תימא גידולי גידולין, v'chi teima gidulei
gidulin, we're talking about a second derivative, ומאי קמשמע לן, u'mai kamashmalan,
and what does it teach me? בדבר שאין זרעו כלה b'davar she'ein
zar'o kalah when the original seed is not destroyed even the second
derivative is תרומה, Terumah, הא נמי תנינא, ha nami tanina, we also
taught that in the משנה, Mishnah, הטבל גידוליו מותרין בדבר שזרעו כלה.
ha'tevel gidulav mutarin b'davar
she'zar'o kalah.
By טבל Tevel actually, טבל Tevel is more lenient than תרומה, Terumah,
which by the way indicates that this whole thing is rabbinic if
we're distinguishing between טבל Tevel and תרומה. Terumah. And if you take
טבל, Tevel, you take a piece of grain that has not had
תרומות ומעשרות Terumos u'Maasros taken from it, it's טבל, Tevel, and you
plant it and it grows again, is that considered, that's גידולי טבל.
Gidulei Tevel. Is that considered טבל Tevel or not? Now the question
obviously should be who cares, right? I take this piece of grain
that has not had תרומות ומעשרות Terumos u'Maasros taken from it, it's
טבל, Tevel, I plant it, and something grows. So if it's connected
to the earlier grain it's טבל. Tevel. Forget if it's not connected
to the earlier grain, it's טבל. Tevel. So who cares? So the
only reason you should care says רש"י Rashi is the following: The
original piece of grain was after I had winnowed and threshed and
whatever made the whole thing into a mound and that is considered
once the מלאכה melachah was done on the original grain,
it's טבל Tevel of גמר מלאכה g'mar melachah after the גמר מלאכה
g'mar melachah where there you can't even eat from it אכילת עראי.
achilas arai. But new grain that grows that has not been through
that whole process and I go and I just pluck a few
kernels of grain before גמר מלאכה g'mar melachah I can pop them
into my mouth, you're allowed to eat אכילת עראי. achilas arai. So
therefore the difference is, if it's connected to the original kernel you
can't eat this new stalk even אכילת עראי. achilas arai. If it's
considered brand new you can eat it אכילת עראי, achilas arai, that's
the whole difference. So we say you know what גידולי טבל Gidulei
Tevel you don't have to worry about. Okay, which by the way
is a good indication unless you come up with a better reason
that even the problem of גידולי תרומה Gidulei Terumah is only rabbinic
because you should be consistent, either what grows from the grain should
be considered continuation or it should be considered something new, what's the
logic of distinguishing? Fine, but by טבל Tevel we're more lenient than
תרומה Terumah and what grows by תרומה Terumah we're stricter, by טבל
Tevel we say that what grows is not considered to be like
the original טבל. Tevel. However, the משנה Mishnah goes
on, it says אבל בדבר שזרעו כלה, aval b'davar she'zar'o kalah, that's
when the original seed has been destroyed like it was from a
kernel of wheat, but but בדבר שאין זרעו כלה, aval bedavar she'ein
zar'o kaleh, when the original seed has not been destroyed, original seed,
אפילו גידולי גידולים אסורים באכילה, afilu gidulei gidulim assurim be'achilah, even the
second generations or like the extra bulbs according to Rashi would be
a problem. So even by טבל Tevel we're more lenient, we're strict
by... we're strict when אין זרעו כלה, ein zar'o kaleh, when the
original thing remains even the second generation, so certainly by תרומה. Terumah.
So basically to summarize what's going on, he says, who's the he?
I forgot already,
רבא בר מתנא Rava bar Masna says to these two guys, he
says what's פשט? pshat? How come it says it stops being טמא
tamei but it's אסור באכילה? assur be'achilah? And they say no, no,
no, אסור באכילה assur be'achilah just means it's still תרומה. Terumah. And
he says we already know that. We know that once you plant
something what continues to grow remains תרומה Terumah even second generation under
some circumstances. So I still don't understand what the חידוש chiddush is.
Okay? Why is it telling me it's not טמא tamei and it's
אסור? assur? And if אסור assur means it's תרומה, Terumah, well it's
obvious that it's תרומה, Terumah, that's not a חידוש. chiddush. Okay so
he basically pushed back. And what did they say to them? He
say back... so אמרו ליה, amru lei, so they were silent. They
didn't have an answer. They said, תאקע, taki, you should come to
the yeshiva with us. That's a good question. You know, next time
you could ask רבא Rava that question. So anyway, no but they
didn't say that. They didn't have an answer, he stumped them.
So אמרו ליה, amru lei, so then they turned around and said
to him, מידי שמיע לך בהא? midi shmia lach beha? Maybe you've
heard a good פשט pshat in this? תאקע, taki, it's a good
question. Maybe you've heard a good פשט? pshat?
So מידי שמיע לך בהא? midi shmia lach beha? אמר להו, amar
lehu, he said back to them, הכי אמר רב ששת. hachi amar
Rav Sheshet. Yeah, let me tell you what רב ששת Rav Sheshet
says, okay? It's almost like, you know, dueling rabbis. Your rabbi says
that, let me tell you what my rabbi says. Here's what רב
ששת Rav Sheshet says about this: מאי אסורין? mai assurim? What does
it mean that after you plant them they remain forbidden? Not that
they're תרומה, Terumah, that's obvious. What does it mean they remain forbidden?
אסורין לכהנים, assurin lechohanim, that even כהנים kohanim can't eat them now.
Why not? Why can't כהנים kohanim eat them? I mean, we're talking
about... you planted תרומה טמאה. Terumah tmeah. It loses its טומאה. tumah.
Right? This is what the משנה mishna said: it's no longer טמא
tamei but you can't eat it. But if it's no longer טמא,
tamei, right, why can't you eat it? So the first answer was
זרים zarim can't eat it. He says it's obvious, it's תרומה. Terumah.
So can't eat it presumably means a כהן kohen still can't eat
it. Now why can't a כהן kohen eat it if it stops
being טמא? tamei? That was the question we originally had. So I'll
tell you רב ששת Rav Sheshet says yes, the whole point of
the משנה mishna is like it sounds like: it stops being טמא
tamei but it remains forbidden to the כהנים. kohanim. Now why is
that? הואיל ואפסלו להו בהיסח הדעת, ho'il ve'ifsalu lehu behessech hada'as, because
it becomes פסול passul not through טומאה tumah but through היסח הדעת.
hessech hada'as. What does היסח הדעת hessech hada'as mean? Lack of attention.
Basically כהנים kohanim are supposed to protect their תרומה Terumah from becoming
טמא. tamei. Right? It says, you know, it says משמרת תרומתי, mishmeret
terumoti, so the guarding, the protecting of my תרומה. Terumah. They stopped
paying attention to it as soon as it became טמא. tamei. They
said, alright, it's טמא, tamei, we don't have to pay attention anymore,
what's going to happen to it? So they just ignored it. So
now even when the טומאה tumah goes away by planting it, it
remains invalid because of this פסול psul called היסח הדעת, hessech hada'as,
lack of attention. Lack of attention becomes its own פסול psul in
itself. Okay? And therefore even when the טומאה tumah goes away, it
still is פסול passul as היסח הדעת. hessech hada'as. Now that's a
wild idea because you would assume what's the reason to pay attention
to it? To prevent it from becoming טמא. tamei. So as long
as you've addressed the טומאה tumah issue, this doesn't operate independently as
a פסול. psul. So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to
say. So he says,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: הניחא, hanicha, that's good למאן
דאמר היסח הדעת פסול הגוף הוי. leman d'amar hessech hada'as psul hagoof
havei. I'm sorry, פסול הגוף הוי. psul hagoof havei. That's good if
היסח הדעת hessech hada'as is an intrinsic invalidation. So therefore it stopped
being טמא, tamei, but since you had stopped paying attention to it,
it retains the invalidity of היסח הדעת. hessech hada'as. אלא למאן דאמר
היסח הדעת פסול טומאה הוי, ela leman d'amar hessech hada'as psul tumah
havei, but if היסח הדעת hessech hada'as whole problem is that it
might have become טמא tamei and the whole concern of not paying
attention is טומאה, tumah, מאי איכא למימר? mai ika lemeimar? Then you
don't have a good explanation because then if it gets rid of
the טומאה, tumah, then any היסח הדעת hessech hada'as was only a
related issue of טומאה. tumah. And how do we know this is
debated?
דאתמר, d'itmar, it was taught: היסח הדעת, hessech hada'as, what's the story
when we say that there's a problem of היסח הדעת hessech hada'as
by תרומה, Terumah, lack of attention? רבי יוחנן אמר פסול טומאה הוי,
Rabbi Yochanan amar psul tumah havei, it's a פסול psul of טומאה,
tumah, it's a concern that it became
טמא. tamei. וריש לקיש אמר פסול הגוף הוי, veReish Lakish amar psul
hagoof havei, no it's an intrinsic invalidity.
רבי יוחנן אמר פסול טומאה הוי, Rabbi Yochanan amar psul tumah havei,
שאם יבוא אליהו ויטהרנה שומעין לו. she'im yavo Eliyahu veyitaharena shomin lo.
If Eliyahu were to come, which is a way of saying if
we were to have like a video camera, like we would say,
you know, if somebody had got it on their cell phone, right?
If we had obvious knowledge that nothing had happened, even though you
weren't paying attention, it would be טהור, tahor, it would be fine.
The only problem of היסח הדעת hessech hada'as is it might have
been טמא. tamei. If we would know for sure it wasn't טמא,
tamei, then that... it would not be a problem. שומעין לו, shomin
lo, you would listen to him. וריש לקיש אמר פסול הגוף הוי,
veReish Lakish amar psul hagoof havei, no, it's an intrinsic invalidity, שאם
יבוא אליהו ויטהרנה אין שומעין לו. she'im yavo Eliyahu veyitaharena ein shomin
lo. That even if Eliyahu would come, you would not listen to
him. Yes, it's not טמא, tamei, but... It is פסול pasul and
what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said, that's according to ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish I have פשט pshat in the משנה mishna to have this
תרומה טמאה, teruma tmeiah, you plant it, it stops being טמא, tamei,
you know what that's like? That's like אליהו הנביא Eliyahu Hanavi came
because now we know it's not טמא, tamei, but it doesn't matter
since you had stopped paying attention to it, it remains פסול pasul
because of הסח הדעת, hesech hadaas, Charlie.
Yeah, I had two questions. One going back to the second generation
saying we had the case in חולין Chullin of the בן פקועה.
ben pakuah. בן
פקועה ben pakuah and would that not be a similarity?
Yeah, we don't, גידולי גידולין gidulei gidulin I mean whatever, yes and
no, meaning A, there's a difference between we're talking about animals and
not plants, and also it's like a זכר ונקבה zecher unekeiva whatever
and B it's an issue, I mean whatever, it's an issue it's
a different area, you know, טרפות, treifos, other things, so there's a
rough analogy but there's always a lot of distinctions to be made,
yeah.
Second question is if I if I put if I put the
seed in the ground and it's growing, it can't become טמא tamei
until it's harvested, it's attached to the ground. So what does this
attention mean?
I didn't have to watch my seed. No, no, no, no, no,
no. What happened was is I have my pile of grain and
it became טמא, tamei, right? My grain תרומה teruma became טמא tamei
and then I said, "Ach, now that's I can't do anything with
it now. What am I going to do, burn it? Whatever, the
heck with it." And I just started ignoring it. And a week
later my wife came and said, "You know what, why don't you
just at least plant it?" I said, "Oh, that's a good idea,"
and I went and I planted it. Okay, and then it stopped
being טמא tamei because I planted it. But for the last week
I haven't been paying attention to it, so it retains the פסול
psul of הסח הדעת hesech hadaas that I have not been protective
of its status for the last week.
But it was already טמא! tamei!
Yes, but according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish there's a new פסול
psul called הסח הדעת. hesech hadaas.
That's exactly, that's his exact point. רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says, "I
don't get it, it's no worse than טומאה." tumah. Okay, that's exactly
the point. Now I would say by the way it's interesting to
think about this as a little bit of an analogy, right? You
know, okay I'll give it I'll give an example with with Avi.
So my wife tells me, "Go watch the kids in the playground."
So I take the kids to the playground and I spend the
whole time reading my book and she comes back an hour later
and she says, "What are you doing? You weren't watching them!" "Yeah,
but they're okay, nothing happened," right? So that's like the debate of
רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, right? It's all just
a matter of something happening. So if nothing happened, I didn't do
anything wrong, you know. But others will say no, there's an intrinsic
פסול, psul, הסח הדעת, hesech hadaas, right? The whole point is you're
supposed to pay attention. It doesn't matter if something happens or doesn't
happen, the lack of intention is an intrinsic problem. You didn't pay
attention to it, that's some intrinsic פסול. psul. So that's ריש לקיש's
Reish Lakish position. What so, so this works according to ריש לקיש,
Reish Lakish, it doesn't work according to רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. Okay,
so let's take a look. Now first we're going to finish the
debate of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan trying
to prove their point. איתיביה Eisivei רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan לריש לקיש.
leReish Lakish. רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan challenged ריש לקיש Reish Lakish to
prove that there was this problem, that there was no special problem
of הסח הדעת, hesech hadaas, it was all just about the problem
of טומאה. tumah. רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה אומר,
Rebbi Yishmael bno shel Rebbi Yochanan ben Beroka omer, Rebbi Yishmael the
son of Rebbi Yochanan ben Beroka would say, לול קטן היה, Lul
katan haya, there was a little like a like a funnel, like
a little like a whatever, בין כבש למזבח, bein keves lemizbe'ach, between
the ramp and the altar, במערבה של כבש, bima'arava shel keves, in
the west of the ramp, ששם היו זורקים פסולי חטאת
העוף, shesham hayu zorkim psulei chatas ha'of, there you were
throwing
birds' sin offerings that became invalid, ותעבור צורתן, veta'avor tzurasan, and you
would wait till their their sort of appearance would pass by, which
is an idiomatic expression, it means that it would become nightfall and
they would become invalid by לינה, lina, I'll unpack this in a
minute, ויוצאין לבית השרפה, veyotzin leveit hasreifa, and then you would take
them out to be burned.
The first thing I want to show you where this would occur,
right?
Because I I've Is this in the משנה mishna too or just
in the בית המקדש? Beit Hamikdash?
Where? This is in the משנה. mishna. No. Oh, okay.
Anyway, so here's your בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. Okay,
whatever, this is the אולם ulam whatever, but anyway, this is the
עזרה. azara. Here's your altar with the corners,
and here's your fire. Okay, there's your altar, right? And the ramp.
Okay, so where would you do a חטאת העוף? chatas ha'of? The
חטאת העוף chatas ha'of sacrifice would be done here, okay? They have
little pillars, whatever. Anyway,
there's the חטאת העוף chatas ha'of sacrifice in the southwest corner. So
you see here, right over here, we've got it's the west of
the ramp, right? It's on the west side of the ramp, and
because of the way the ramp is situated, it's the southwest corner.
This is where the כהן kohein would stand to do those bird
sacrifices, those חטאת העוף chatas ha'of on the on the floor. So
here he is, he's doing the bird sacrifice, something happens that invalidates
it. Okay, now, normally when a קרבן korban becomes פסול, pasul, you
burn it. But as we're about to see, this is a type
of a פסול psul which is somehow not seen as intrinsic enough
that it allows you to burn the bird right away. So what
you do, in cases where there's a little like of a of
a quasi פסול, psul, you can't bring it but you can't burn
it right away because it's not fully פסול pasul or, you know,
intrinsically פסול, psul, you wait till the following morning, then it becomes
invalid because of לינה. lina. What happens because of something נותר notar
becomes leftover? Any animal, because if you left over קרבן korban once
it's slaughtered. And therefore you burn it because it's נותר notar and
it becomes intrinsically פסול. psul. So you intentionally leave it over and
allow it to become intrinsically פסול psul so that—פסול—so pasul then you
can burn it. So it says there would be a little thing
in the floor that when something happens to the bird, you'd throw
it in that little thing in the floor, you'd wait the night,
you'd scoop it out the next morning, it would become פסול pasul
and then you would burn it. Right away?
Yeah, not there.
I mean you'd burn it—you'd still burn it on, you know, Temple
grounds because we learned that even at the begin—you know, earlier, right,
that anything שפסולו בקודש shepsulo bekodesh and this is a חטאת, chatas,
a חטאת chatas doesn't leave the Temple grounds. But, you know, but
you would not do it like literally right there. Okay, so now
it says like this.
That probably smell terrible.
I'm
sure, well they had a—they had a
major barbecue going on here.
I mean they had a bunch of meat in the
sun and
it's... Oh, that's true. That's true. Okay, okay. ושם היו זורקין פסולי
חטאת העוף עד שתעבור צורתה. V'sham hayu zorkin psulei chatas ha'of ad
sheta'avor tzurata.
You would wait till this idea of their—of their sort of their
appearance would pass over, which is a way of saying you wait
the night till they become invalid with לינה, linah, with נותר, notar,
ויוצאין לבית השריפה v'yotzin l'veit hasreifah and then you'd burn them. Now,
אי אמרת—now ee amart what is this invalidity that is not enough
to burn it on its own? Pretty much any invalidity you can
think of is an intrinsic invalidity and you should burn it. Why
should you have to wait over the night? So let's take a
look. אי אמרת בשלמא פסול טומאה הוי—so Ee amart bishlama psul tuma
havei they assume without even saying it that the only invalidity we
could be talking about that isn't an intrinsic one is this problem
of היסח הדעת. hesech hadaas. And if היסח הדעת hesech hadaas is
a problem by תרומה, truma, right, not paying attention because it might
become טמא tamei or whatever, היסח הדעת hesech hadaas is a problem
by קרבנות korbanos as well, certainly all the more so by קרבנות.
korbanos. So the גמרא Gemara imagines the only invalidity we could be
talking about is היסח הדעת. hesech hadaas. Now, if it's—if היסח הדעת
hesech hadaas itself is an intrinsic invalidity, so also burn it. Why
wait the next morning? The only explanation here of something that's a
quasi-problem is it would be היסח הדעת hesech hadaas which is—we don't
know it's טמא tamei but it might be טמא. tamei. And therefore
we can't bring it, but we can't burn it, and therefore we
have to wait the next morning. So that shows you that היסח
הדעת hesech hadaas is a טומאה tuma problem, not an intrinsic problem,
or else you could just burn it right now. So let's take
a look. אי אמרת, Ee amart, if you say בשלמא
פסול טומאה הוי, bishlama psul tuma havei, that היסח הדעת hesech hadaas
is a טומאה tuma type of a problem, it might be טמא,
tamei, משום הכי בעי עיבור צורה. mishum hachi ba'i ibur tzurah. Therefore
you have to wait till the night passes over and it becomes
פסול pasul as נותר notar because it's not a strong enough problem
to burn it right now. Why? שמא יבוא אליהו ויטהרנה—because Shema yavo
Eliyahu viyitaharena it might be טהור tahor and then it won't be
a problem even if you weren't paying attention to it. אלא אי
אמרת פסול הגוף, Ella ee amart psul haguf, but if you say
it's an intrinsic invalidity, למה לי עיבור צורה—then lama li ibur tzurah
any intrinsic invalidity you should burn right now. ותנן, V'hasnan, we taught
in the
משנה, Mishna, זה הכלל, zeh haklal, this is the rule. כל שפסולו
בגופו, Kol shepsulo begufo, anything that has an intrinsic invalidity, ישרף מיד,
yisarev miyad, you burn right away. ודם ובבעלים, V'dam uvabailim, now there
are categories of things that are invalid that you have to wait
till the next morning. If it's not in the meat itself, you
can't burn the meat but not because of a problem in the
meat, because of a problem external to the meat. What would be
a problem external to the meat that you can't burn the meat
so—or eat the meat if
a whatever—ודם ובבעלים תעבור צורתן ויוצאין לבית השריפה. v'dam uvabailim ta'avor tzuratan
v'yotzin l'veit hasreifa. If the problem was with the blood or with
the owners. In that case, the—the meat couldn't be eaten or couldn't
be burned, so in that case you would have to—but not because
of a problem in the meat, and therefore you'd have to wait
till the next morning. Now what's the scenario of ודם ובבעלים? v'dam
uvabailim? דם Dam is the easiest one. דם Dam is the blood
spilled or the blood became טמא. tamei. So if you can't do
זריקת הדם, zerikas hadam, the קרבן's korban invalid. So what do you
do with the meat? Well, you have to burn it, but there's
no problem in the meat per se, the problem was external to
the meat. So in that case, fine, wait till the next morning.
בעלים, Bailim, similar, let's say for example the בעלים bailim died, right,
and then—well that depends which type of קרבן, korban, most קרבנות korbanot
you can bring even if the בעלים bailim are dead, but how
about a חטאת, chatas, okay? So חטאת המתה. chatas hamaisa. Right, so
anyway, exactly.
So what do you do?
You can't offer
it but it's not like intrinsic something happened to the meat, it
happened external to the meat. So that's a case where you have
to wait for it to become invalid, it becomes intrinsically פסול pasul
to burn it. So now the question you should be asking is,
okay, so why did you assume this bird problem was a היסח
הדעת hesech hadaas problem? Maybe the bird problem was a problem because
of דם dam or בעלים, bailim, and that's why we had to
wait till the next morning. What's the whole question to begin with?
The תוספות Tosafot says ah, here's the question though. Here's the question,
very ingenious. He says okay, let's say it was that scenario of
דם dam or בעלים. bailim. You have this bird, you're ready to
bring it, you spill the blood, okay, you have to wait till
the next morning. What do you do with the bird now? What
do we say you do with it? You throw it in the
hole, right, and you wait. So he now says as soon as
you've thrown it in the hole and walked away, היסח הדעת! hesech
hadaas! Why do you have to wait till the next morning? Turn
around and come back and burn it right now!
Anytime—why would you ever have to wait to the next morning even
if it's
a
scenario... So you see that הסח הדעת hesech hadaas is not an
intrinsic פסול psul or you would always be entitled to burn these
things right away. One minute, let's just read his let's just read
the answer. אמר ליה, Amar lei, האי תנא
תנא דבי רבה בר אבוה הוא. hai tanna tanna devei Rabba bar
Avuha hu. You know what? That's a very good question, but the
author of this משנה mishna is the one who teaches is the
תנא tanna of from the house of Rabba bar Avuha, דאמר אפילו
פיגול טעון עיבור צורה de'amar afilu pigul taun ibbur tzurah that everything,
even if it's intrinsically invalid, you know, things you have to wait
till the next morning. So it's not just some things you wait
and some things you don't and as soon as it becomes intrinsically
invalid, you should be able to burn it right away. Actually, everything
you're entitled to burn right everything even intrinsically invalid things you have
to wait till the next morning, and that's what's going on here.
But you know what? You're actually right. If we were to hold
of the position that intrinsically invalid things you could burn right away,
then as soon as there was הסח הדעת hesech hadaas you could
burn it, you would not have to wait till the next morning.
Yes.
Where is the היתר heter for deliberately
doing, yeah, creating נותר, nosar, that's a question, or deliberately הסח הדעת?
hesech hadaas? I don't know, there's no like איסור issur of הסח
הדעת, hesech hadaas, although you can ask another question, where's the היתר
heter being over on the on the איסור issur of נותר nosar
of לא תותירו ממנו עד בוקר? lo sosiru mimenu ad boker? But
there you could say you don't have any choice, you're not allowed
to eat it, right? Because, but maybe the choice is to burn
it, but you're not allowed to burn it, so you're sort of
like an אנוס onus in that regard. All right. So that's the
debate of רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש, Rabbi Yochanan veReish Lakish, we're not
done.
איתיבי, Eisvei,
now, נטמא או שנפסל הבשר או שיצא חוץ לקלעים. nitma o shenipsal
habasar o sheyatza chutz laklaim. Here's another challenge to this idea of
what's intrinsic פסול. psul. Okay, we taught in a ברייתא beraisa that
if the meat became טמא tamei or it became invalid. Now what
does invalid mean? What other invalidity is it? So או שיצא חוץ
לקלעים, o sheyatza chutz laklaim, another possibility is that the meat was
taken out of temple grounds, out of the עזרה azarah because if
we're talking about a קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim like a חטאת chatas
that can only be eaten on the temple grounds itself. So how
would the meat become טמא? tamei? Two basic possibilities or become unable
to be eaten. Two basic scenarios: one it became טמא tamei and
the other it was taken off of temple grounds. But this mentions
a third thing: or it became פסול. pasul. So we're going to
have to figure out what that third scenario is, but anyway in
any one of these three cases, what's the הלכה? halacha? So now
you have not yet done the זריקת הדם zrikas hadam of the
קרבן, korban, but the בשר basar can no longer be eaten. Do
you go ahead and do זריקת הדם zrikas hadam for קרבן korban
when the בשר basar can't be eaten? This is a fascinating question,
right? Because mostly I mean the basic way the basic thing that
makes a קרבן korban good, you're יוצא, yotzei, you got you know,
your כפרה kaparah is the זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. So and the
בשר basar is seen as somewhat secondary except for קרבן פסח, Korban
Pesach, which we'll get to later in this מסכת. maseches.
Didn't we learn that the קרבן korban meat is what makes the
כפרה?
kaparah? Yeah, so it's it's a component of the כפרה, kaparah, but
it's not a necessary component. The primary thing is the דם. dam.
So what happens if you can't do the בשר basar at all?
Are you entitled to do the דם dam if even from the
get-go if that's the only thing that's going to be happening with
this קרבן? korban? So the בשר basar is טמא, tamei, what do
you do? So it's a debate of תנאים. tannaim. רבי אליעזר אומר
יזרוק, Rabbi Eliezer omer yizrok, you should do the זריקת הדם zrikas
hadam even without the meat. רבי יהושע אומר לא יזרוק, Rabbi Yehoshua
omer lo yizrok, you should not do it. ומודי רבי יהושע, Umodi
Rabbi Yehoshua, but Rabbi Yehoshua does concede that even though he says
don't do it if you don't have the meat, שאם זרק הורצה,
she'im zarak hurtzah, that if you did the זריקה, zrikah, then the
קרבן korban you are יוצא. yotzei. Why? Because as we're going to
see at least by טומאה tumah there's an idea that the ציץ
tzitz is מרצה. mratzeh. Right, what does the תורה Torah tell you
the idea of the ציץ tzitz by the כהן? kohen? It says,
right, that he wears it, right, and he's being נושא עון הקדשים,
nosei avon hakodashim, the sin of the sacrifices. So חז"ל Chazal understand
that problems relating to טומאה tumah בדיעבד bedieved if they were done,
the fact that the כהן גדול kohen gadol wears the ציץ tzitz
is enough to basically say בדיעבד bedieved it works. So even though
you shouldn't do it, ultimately it's related to a problem of טומאה
tumah of the meat, so בדיעבד bedieved if you did it, it's
okay. Okay, so there's this debate about what do you do if
the meat is not valid. Now not valid is for three reasons
again: טומאה, tumah, יוצא חוץ לקלעים, yotza chutz laklaim, it was taken
off of the temple grounds, and the third answer is נפסל. nipsal.
Scenario is נפסל. nipsal. Now what's this
נפסל? nipsal? What other thing could go wrong with the meat other
than טומאה tumah and being taken away? לאו בהסח הדעת? lav behesech
hadaas? Presumably the only third thing possible that could happen to this
meat is the הסח הדעת hesech hadaas problem. So if we're talking
about הסח הדעת, hesech hadaas, let's take a look. אי אמרת בשלמא
פסולי טומאה הוי, ei amarta bishlama psulei tumah havai, again Rabbi Yochanan
says look, if הסח הדעת hesech hadaas was related to the world
of טומאה tumah then, you know, and was a concern of טומאה,
tumah, then I get it under then I understand why בדיעבד bedieved
it's okay.
היינו דמשתכחת ליה דמרצי ציץ. hainu d'mishtachas lei d'mirtzei tzitz. That's why
the ציץ tzitz atones for it בדיעבד. bedieved. So Rabbi Yehoshua says
don't do it לכתחילה, lechatchila, בדיעבד bedieved it'll be okay. Why? Because
either it's a טומאה tumah problem or it's a הסח הדעת hesech
hadaas problem, which is like a טומאה tumah problem, which is essentially
a טומאה tumah problem. That's Rabbi Yochanan. So it makes sense to
me why according to Rabbi Yehoshua he would concede that בדיעבד *bedieved*
it's okay if it was only related to טומאה tumah, *tumah*. אלא
*ella*, but according to you ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, *Reish Lakish*, אי
אמרת פסול הגוף הוי *i amart psul haguf havei*, if this idea
of היסח הדעת hesech hadaat? *heisech hadaas* is some new intrinsic invalidity,
אמאי הורצה *amai hurtza*, why בדיעבד *bedieved* is it okay if you
went ahead and brought it according to רבי יהושע *Rebbi Yehoshua*? It
wasn't a טומאה tumah. *tumah* problem, why does the ציץ *tzitz* give
you a pass? Why is it okay? So ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*
says, you know what, you're right. If it was היסח הדעת hesech
hadaat *heisech hadaas*, it would be a problem בדיעבד *bedieved*. But מאי
נפסל *mai nifsal*, when it says a third scenario, טומאה tumah. *tumah*,
going outside of the temple grounds, and נפסל *nifsal*, נפסל *nifsal* is
not the scenario of היסח הדעת *heisech hadaas*. מאי נפסל *mai nifsal*?
נפסל בטבול יום *nifsal betvul yom*. It means that a טמא tamei
*tamei* person touched it. Now, it's not a טמא tamei, *tamei* person
that's a full טמא tamei, *tamei* person because we already mentioned טמא
tamei, *tamei*. It's a very, it's a very sort of, you know,
tenuous טומאה tumah. *tumah*. Somebody who was טמא tamei *tamei*, he had
gone to the מקוה mikvah? *mikvah*, he was waiting for nightfall to
become totally טהור tahor. *tahor*. His טומאה *tumah* is very low level,
it's like a שני *sheini*, it's even in some ways maybe even
weaker. And he touches this, this meat. So when it said נפסל
*nifsal* because you should know by the way, it is not a,
it is not a bad answer. No, but okay,
it's not a bad answer because often we use the word טמא
tamei *tamei* and פסול *pasul* to refer to something is טמא tamei.
*tamei* when it has a level of טומאה *tumah* that it can
pass on. It's פסול *pasul* when it has a very low level
of טומאה *tumah* that it cannot pass on. Okay, now that might
not be true here, but the idea to say נטמא או נפסל
*nitma o nifsal*, that נפסל *nifsal* is a lower level of טומאה
*tumah* is something actually that we, is a term that we use.
Okay, so just to take a step back, I know it's getting
a little complicated, but basically רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rebbi Yochanan* says,
look, I'm going to prove to you this isn't an intrinsic problem
because it says if it was נטמא או נפסל *nitma o nifsal*
the meat, then even if you shouldn't throw the blood, בדיעבד *bedieved*
it's okay. So I assume נפסל *nifsal* means היסח הדעת *heisech hadaas*,
and then I can understand why בדיעבד *bedieved* it's okay because טומאה
*tumah* בדיעבד *bedieved* is okay because of the ציץ *tzitz*. But what
do you say ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*, if it's an intrinsic problem,
why should it be okay בדיעבד *bedieved*? He says, no, because I
don't think נפסל *nifsal* means היסח הדעת *heisech hadaas*. I think נפסל
*nifsal* means another type of טומאה *tumah*, and therefore in the end
it's just two variations of טומאה *tumah*. And then it's the הלכה
*halacha* that בדיעבד *bedieved* it's okay because of the ציץ *tzitz*. Okay,
so that's what the גמרא Gemara *gemara* is going to say. Okay,
מאי נפסל *mai nifsal*? נפסל בטבול יום *nifsal betvul yom*, it means
touched by a טבול יום *tvul yom*, so it's a low level
of טומאה *tumah*, but it's a variation of טומאה *tumah*. אי הכי
*ihachi*, says the גמרא Gemara *gemara*, היינו טמא tamei? *hainu tamei*? So
it's just טמא tamei, *tamei*, so we've already said טמא tamei. *tamei*.
Fine, תרי גווני טמא tamei. *terei gavnei tamei*. Okay, fine, two variations
of טמא tamei. *tamei*. So basically, he says you're right, but it
doesn't bother me. You know, often the משנה mishnah. *mishna* lists a
multiple list of things even though you could have inferred it from
the first. So just one second, so where are we? We are
the following. We've got a debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. *Rebbi
Yochanan* and ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*, what this idea of היסח הדעת
*heisech hadaas* is. ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* says this powerful new idea
that היסח הדעת *heisech hadaas* is an intrinsic invalidity even if it
didn't become טמא tamei? *tamei*. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rebbi Yochanan* says,
no, no, give me a break. It's only because maybe it's טמא
tamei, *tamei*. All the evidence seems to side with רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan *Rebbi Yochanan*. The idea, it's like a fascinating idea ריש לקיש
*Reish Lakish*, but it seems to come out of nowhere. All the
evidence seems to side with רבי יוחנן *Rebbi Yochanan*, that it's not
a new פסול *psul*, it's a type of a concern of טומאה
*tumah*. What was this related to? Going, this goes back to the
question of when you take the תרומה terumah. *truma*, טמא tamei *tamei*
תרומה terumah. *truma* grain and plant it, why does the grain that's
now no longer טמא *tamei* remain אסור *assur*? And the answer was,
oh, because of a new problem of היסח הדעת *heisech hadaas* that
occurred to it even when the טומאה *tumah* goes away. So the
answer is, that's very nice according to ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* who
thinks there is this new problem of היסח הדעת *heisech hadaas*, but
according to רבי יוחנן *Rebbi Yochanan* who makes a much more reasonable
argument, a much more supported argument that היסח הדעת *heisech hadaas* is
only a concern of טומאה *tumah*, we're back to square one. If
the טומאה *tumah* goes away, the grain should now become permissible. So
we still don't have a good פשט peshat *pshat* in this משנה
mishnah. *mishna*. Yeah, you had a question?
And for if it's חוץ לקלעים *chutz lakalaim*?
Oh, okay, good, I was trying to also over that. So yes,
there is another case that actually בדיעבד *bedieved* it's okay that's not
טומאה *tumah*, it's חוץ לקלעים *chutz lakalaim*. So רש"י *Rashi* and תוספות
*Tosafot* both discuss that, that we learn out somewhere else that because
again that's seen as something like a more extrinsic problem. It's not
so much, you know, something happened to the meat, although it did
happen, it went outside, but it's more about location than the status
of the meat, somehow we learn that that also בדיעבד *bedieved* is
okay. But you're right, it's a good question, right? Because חוץ לקלעים
*chutz lakalaim* also is a problem that's not, you know, that's not
טומאה *tumah* that gets solved. Okay, so now we still don't understand
this משנה mishnah. *mishna* why the תרומה terumah *truma* remains a problem
after you planted it. So כי סליק רבין *ki salik Ravin*, when
רבין *Ravin* went to ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, אמרה להא שמעתא קמיה
דרבי ירמיה *amrah leha shemaata kammei deRebbi Yirmeya*, he told over this
discussion to רבי ירמיה *Rebbi Yirmeya*. The two answers we've given, neither
of which are satisfying. One was to say it was still תרומה
terumah *truma* and the answer was that's obvious, and the other is
to say it's a problem of היסח הדעת *heisech hadaas* and the
answer was, yeah, but that's not an intrinsic problem. So we still
don't know פשט peshat *pshat* in this משנה mishnah. *mishna*. So what
did רבי ירמיה *Rebbi Yirmeya* say? ואמר רבי ירמיה *Veamar Rebbi Yirmeya*,
בבלאי טפשאי *Bavlaei tipshai*,
stupid Babylonians, משום דיתבי בארעא דחשוכא *mishum deyatvei beara dechashoka*, because they
dwell in a dark land because בבל *Bavel* is very like low
level, you know, lowlands and... Therefore it doesn't get as much sunlight.
אמריתו שמעתא דמחשכא *Amreitu shema'ata de-machshakhu* because you live in a dark
land, you say over a discussion that's dark, that doesn't have enough
light shed upon it. Because you try to explain this משנה mishnah
*mishna* without really understanding it. Now רש״י *Rashi* has a very sharp
line. If you look at the first wide line of רש״י *Rashi*
he says, שמעתא דמחשכן *shema'ata de-machshakan* and רש״י *Rashi* says, כשאין יודעים
טעמו של דבר *keshein yodim tamo shel davar*, if you don't know
the reason for something, בונים מליבם טעם שאינו *bonim mi-libam ta'am she-eino*,
you just make something up. So they didn't know פשט *pshat* in
this משנה Mishnah *mishna*, so they made stuff up.
Oh, it's still תרומה terumah? *truma*, היסח הדעת *hesech hadas*. It's because
you don't know enough, you make up these reasons. I'm going to
tell you what's going on here. לא שמיע לכו
*Lo shemi'a l'chu* and here's the point of the idea of dark
like lack of knowledge. You just didn't have enough pieces of information
at your disposal.
You did not hear or did you not hear הדר ריש לקיש
בשמיה דרבי יאשיה *Had Reish Lakish b'shmei de-Rabbi Yoshia*? The following statement
of ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* in the name of רבי יאשיה *Rabbi
Yoshia*, right, and ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* and רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshia*
are ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. So you're in בבל *Bavel*, you did
not hear this teaching. And here's the teaching: מי חג שנטמאו *Mei
chag she-nitme'u*. You have water on פסח *Pesach*, right, and they would
do a special thing of ניסוך המים nisuch hamayim *Nisuch Ha-mayim* and
they'd pour it on the מזבח mizbeach *mizbe'ach*. Now it became טמא
*tamei*. And it's שבת *Shabbos*, so you can't go out and draw
new water. What are you going to do to make this water
usable for ניסוך המים *Nisuch Ha-mayim*? השיקן ואחר כך הקדישן טהורין *hishikun
v'achar hikdishan tehorin*. If you literally like kissed them, meaning what that
means is if you have water that is טמא *tamei*, and this
is something that only works by water because you cannot do this
by normal foods. If you have an apple that's טמא *tamei*, you
can't put it in the מקווה *mikva*. It's טמא *tamei*, that's it,
you're stuck. But if you have water that is טמא *tamei* and
you put it in the מקווה *mikva* in a vessel and the
water level evens so that it's evened out with the top level
of the vessel where the water is like submerged and it's even
with the top level of the water, that's called השקה *Hashaka*, which
is like literally kissing, but it's basically like you have connected it
to the water, made it one with the water, and because it's
not just immersed in the water but actually becomes מקווה *mikva* water,
then there's a special הלכה *halacha* that then it loses its טומאה
*tumah* status and it becomes טהור tahor, *tahor*. So now you've got
this water you've got to use for the ניסוך המים *Nisuch Ha-mayim*.
It became טמא *tamei*. It's שבת *Shabbos*, you can't draw new stuff.
Your only option is to do this השקה *Hashaka*, to immerse it
in the מקווה *mikva*. השיקן ואחר כך הקדישן טהורין *hishikun v'achar hikdishan
tehorin*. If first you did the השקה *Hashaka* and then you sanctified
the water, it had not yet been sanctified, טהורין *tehorin*, then it's
fine. הקדישן ואחר כך השיקן *hikdishan v'achar hishikun*, if you first had
sanctified it and then you did the השקה *Hashaka*, so it was
same thing, but it was קודש kodesh, *kodesh* that was טמא *tamei*,
then טמאים *tme'in*, then this does not work. So basically why not?
In either way you did the exact process that should make it
טהור tahor? *tahor*. In one case it was קודש kodesh. *kodesh*, in
the other case not, but either way it should become טהור tahor
*tahor*. מכדי *michti*, let's take a look. זריעה zriah נינהו *zeri'a ninhu*,
and this is again this word of זריעה zriah *zeri'a* because we've
already learned before, right, that planting things in the ground makes it
טהור tahor, *tahor*. So the analog of this in the case of
liquids and water is this זריעה zriah *zeri'a* in the מקווה *mikva*,
as it were, almost planting it in the מקווה *mikva* making it
one with the מקווה *mikva*. So the phrase used for this is
זריעה zriah *zeri'a*, the same way planting in the ground makes something
טהור tahor. *tahor*. זריעה zriah נינהו *zeri'a ninhu*, this is a planting.
מה לי השיקן ואחר כך הקדישן *ma li hishikun v'achar hikdishan*? What
do I care first you did it and the sanctification came after
it became טהור tahor *tahor*? מה לי הקדישן ואחר כך השיקן *ma
li hikdishan v'achar hishikun*? What do I care first you sanctified and
then you did the טהרה taharah *tahara* process? Either way this process
should make it טהור tahor *tahor*. Who cares if it was קודש
kodesh, *kodesh* at the time or not? עלמא *alma*, from ריש לקיש
*Reish Lakish*'s statement what can you see? You can infer אין זריעה
zriah להקדש *ein zeri'a l'hekdesh*, that when things are holy, sanctified, we
don't allow, it's הלכתית *halachically* you're right, it should become טהור tahor?
*tahor*. But it's a special stringency or מעלה *ma'ala*, special status חז״ל
*Chazal* gave to holy things that once a holy thing becomes טמא
*tamei*, you can't make the טומאה *tumah* go off as easily. And
you can understand the idea, like the קודש *kodesh* has been violated.
If a normal thing becomes טמא *tamei* there's no violation, it's just
a status. So you remove the status, you get back to square
one. But if the קודש *kodesh* becomes violated, to then remove the
טומאה *tumah* and have it go back to its קודש *kodesh* status,
there's something problematic about that. Once it's been violated, I'm sorry, it's
all פסול *pasul*, you've got a problem. So you see that even
a process that makes it טהור tahor. *tahor* doesn't work if it
became טמא *tamei* when it was קודש *kodesh*. Now you're understanding the
משנה *mishna* about the תרומה terumah *truma* because what's the case by
the תרומה terumah. *truma*? It was קודש *kodesh*, it was תרומה terumah
*truma*, it became טמא *tamei*, it became violated. So yes, does planting
it make it טהור *tahor*? Yes it does make it טהור *tahor*.
So for all other purposes if this grain touches something else it
won't make it טמא *tamei*. But from the perspective of the תרומה
terumah. *truma* the status still remains. It's still תרומה terumah, טמאה *truma
tmeia* and can't be eaten by כוהנים *Kohanim*. So it's an ironic
status that the grain is טהור *tahor* and if it touches other
things you're okay, but the תרומה terumah *truma* status... has been violated
and it remains considered תרומה truma. טמאה and can't be used the
same way this water, if it became טמא after it was קודש,
can no longer be used on the מזבח mizbeiach. for ניסוך המים
even though the process should really make it טהור. Let me just
read the sentence and then I'll take your question,
Charlie first. It says אלמא אין זריעה להקדש הכא נמי אין זריעה
לתרומה. Alma ein zriah l'hekdesh hacha nami ein zriah l'terumah. The זריעה
zriah does not help the תרומה. truma, Yes, it becomes טהור, but
not enough to restore its status of תרומה טהורה terumah tehorah and
that's why כהנים kohanim cannot eat it. Charlie first, yes?
So the metal vessels in the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, would they
never be put in a מקוה? mikvah, Would it have to be,
if it becomes...
No, vessels can be put in a... oh, no, no, זריעה zriah
doesn't work. That's a good question. That this sort of idea, a
process that it's a good point, a process that actually is about
purifying does work for הקדש, hekdesh, right? You're right. You wouldn't have
it for תרומה. truma תרומה truma is just food so you never
have the option other than planting. Okay, so it's a good question.
Why do we allow a טהרה process which is about putting into
the מקוה, mikvah but we don't allow זריעה zeriah which is not
really about an act of... maybe it's because this is not conceptually
an act of cleansing the טומאה, which is what putting in a
מקוה mikvah, is. It's sort of indirect. We're saying this is a
new object and therefore it doesn't have its old status. Now because
of that you might say it's better. If it's a brand new
object, it's better and it doesn't have the old problems.
But it's not really brand new because it remains תרומה truma and
it remains הקדש. hekdesh. So it's a good question, but you're absolutely
correct. הקדש hekdesh that becomes טמא, of course we can be מטהר
metaher it with מקוה, okay, if it's a vessel. But this type
of indirect way, not a cleansing process but making it planted, that's
something somehow that we say we won't allow by הקדש. hekdesh. Yes?
Why does it also assume that just because it doesn't work for
הקדש hekdesh it shouldn't work for
תרומה?
truma הקדש hekdesh
goes up to רביעי revi'i
and it's not a proof, but it allows us to explain this
משנה. Okay, so he says if you would have had this piece
of teaching of ריש לקיש, you would have had a better way
to explain the משנה.
So the נקודה nekudah then is that it has nothing to do
with היסח הדעת?
Right, right, forget the היסח הדעת answer. It's good, simple פשט of
the משנה. Is it טהור? Yes.
Have you solved the תרומה truma problem? No. This whole thing works
to make it טהור but does not work to restore its תרומה
טהורה terumah tehorah status. But the whole point of the
זריעה was to get rid of the טומאה. Yes, so here you
got...
I understand, so you got rid of it so it won't make
other things טמא, but it itself cannot be eaten, that's פשט of
the משנה. Okay, so יתיב רב דימי וקאמר לה להא שמעתא. Yativ
Rav Dimi veka'amar lah l'ha shema'ata. So now רב דימי Rav Dimi
was sitting and telling over this discussion. Okay, we're still not done.
And but this answer, now we've got a good answer. The answer
is זריעה doesn't work once it's already הקדש, hekdesh, once it's already
תרומה. truma.
But you just said it does, it
did work, in other words... It doesn't work for תרומה truma, purposes.
It works that it's טהור, it won't make other things טמא, but
it doesn't work to restore its status as תרומה טהורה. terumah tehorah.
But the point of the זריעה was to get rid of the
טומאה.
Yeah, so you know what? You didn't succeed. Okay, that's what the
משנה is teaching you. You didn't solve that problem. Okay, so רב
דימי Rav Dimi was sitting and saying over this answer. אמר ליה
אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye wanted to explore this answer.
הקדישן בכלי קאמר Hikdishan bichli ka'amar אבל בפה לא עבדו רבנן מעילה
aval bepeh lo avdu rabanan meilah או דילמא בפה נמי עבדו רבנן
מעילה? o dilma bepeh nami avdu rabanan meilah? Meaning do we say
that if you did it just orally sanctified then it would not
have full status and זריעה would work? Or do we say even
when you orally did it, it gives it full status? Now, this
idea of oral versus vessel is only relevant by things in the
בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. Things in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash like
if you sanctified grain or whatever, even a קרבן, korban, its full
קדושה kedushah comes when you שחט shacht it with the knife which
is a כלי שרת. kli sharet. And certainly things that are not
livestock and animals, things like grain and oil and water and wine,
they become fully sanctified when they're put in the כלי שרת. kli
sharet. When you verbally sanctified it, that's not its yet full status
of קדושה. kedushah. Okay, that's as opposed to תרומה. truma. תרומה, the
only way you sanctify it is verbally. So he's saying like this:
You're saying תרומה has this elevated status and you're saying that this
water,
הקדש hekdesh has this elevated status that זריעה won't work for it.
How about if it's הקדש hekdesh in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash
but it's not the full level of קדושה? kedushah? It's done orally
but it hasn't been put in a כלי שרת? kli sharet? What
will be the status there? So אמר ליה Amar lei he said
back to him, זו לא שמעתי, zu lo shamati, I haven't heard
this, but כיוצא
בה
שמעתי, kiyotzei bah shamati, I have heard something similar. דאמר רבי אבהו
אמר רבי יוחנן d'amar Rabbi Abbahu amar Rabbi Yochanan ענבים שנטמאו, Anavim
shenitme'u, now you see why we're having this whole discussion because we're
getting back to רבי יוחנן's statement of the טמא grapes. Okay, ענבים
שנטמאו, Anavim shenitme'u, that's what this whole thing was to get to
this line. ענבים שנטמאו, Anavim shenitme'u, you have these טמא grapes, דרכן
ואחר כך הקדישן טהורים drachan v'achar kach hikdishan tehorim הקדישן ואחר כך
דרכן טמאים. hikdishan v'achar kach drachan tme'im. Okay, so if you press
them and then sanctified them, then they're טהור. Okay, so if... If
you sanctified them and then pressed the grapes, they are טמא. So
what's the difference? Presumably, the reason they're טהור is why? Meaning, this
connects to the other statement of רבי יוחנן. Why, how could these
grapes be טהור if they were טמא? How could the juice that
comes out be טהור? What did you learn yesterday? All of yesterday?
You do, you do a little bit less than a כביצה. kabeitzah.
Right, so presumably, that's what we're talking about here, that's how it
connects to the whole discussion. And he says, fine, you do little
by little and it's טהור. That's if you wait to sanctify it.
But if you sanctify it first, you've got a problem. Now, why
should that be a problem? Because,
so presumably we're assuming that that's more problematic, the same way זריעה
is more problematic. And it's going to be more problematic if the
stuff is already קודש. It's the same idea. Once something is already
קודש, it's going to be more problematic and these types of tricks
don't work. And therefore he says you have to wait to sanctify
until after the pressing, not before the pressing. So he says, okay,
but והענבים דקדושת פה נינהו, veha'anavim dikdushat peh ninhu, grapes are only
קדושת פה kdushat peh because they're not sanctified, right? You don't, you
don't sanctify grapes, you sanctify the juice, the wine. That's what you're
going to use on the מזבח. So the grapes clearly are just
קדושת פה. kdushat peh. Presumably we think you're sanctifying them for Temple
purposes. ואפילו הכי עבדו רבנן מעלה, ve'afilu hachi avdu rabanan ma'alah, and
even so you see that even though it's only קדושת פה, kdushat
peh, it has not yet turned into the grape, to the juice
and the wine, the Rabbis are strict with it and don't allow
this trick of doing less than a כביצה. kabeitzah. So you see
a similar idea when it's not fully קדוש kadosh by the כלי,
kli, these tricks still can work, I'm sorry, these tricks no longer
work and they're not good. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, Rav
Yosef said, that's not a proof. ענבים קאמרת? Anavim ka'amart? You're talking
about grapes? Who says you're talking about בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash issues?
הכא בענבים של תרומה עסקינן. Hacha be'anavim shel truma askinan. Maybe we're
talking about תרומה. וקדושת פה דידה כקדושת כלי דמיא, ukdushat peh didah
kekdushat kli damya, because by תרומה, verbal sanctification is like the vessel,
that's the full level. Right? Remember the whole way we explained the
משנה of תרומה is we said, ah, once it's תרומה and it
becomes טמא, you can't use these tricks. So we already know by
תרומה the oral sanctification puts it in this level that doesn't let
you use these tricks. And our only, and this maybe that's the
grape case as well. Our question was by the world of קרבנות,
korbanot, the world of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. There, verbal sanctification
is not full sanctification and maybe you should still have some latitude
before it's put in the vessel.
One second, really? So this is טמאי תרומה
ענבים?
tmei truma
anavim?
And somehow you're allowed to get הנאה hana'ah from this?
Well you're not, you're pressing it in the way that you get
out the juice without the juice becoming טמא.
Right, but I'm getting הנאה hana'ah from this תרומה though.
So you, so what, that's fine. Anyway, and not only that, but
the juice isn't טמא. You're a כהן. kohen. I'm not talking about
a non-כהן. kohen. So we're talking about a way to avoid the
טומאה.
He's now making תרומה into הקדש hekdesh essentially, is he not?
No, no, we're not making it into הקדש. hekdesh. You just misunderstood
the case. The case wasn't הקדש, hekdesh, the case was תרומה.
No, but you're allowed to make it הקדש. hekdesh.
No, you're not. הקדשה hekdeisha meaning as תרומה, not as הקדש. hekdesh.
I mean you misunderstood the whole case. This case wasn't about הקדש,
hekdesh, the case was תרומה. It was a תרומה הלכה. truma halacha.
Okay, אבל הני דבעי כלי, aval hani deba'ei kli,
but things like that when we're in the world of הקדש, hekdesh,
if you need a vessel then
you shouldn't be able to question the נסכים? nesachim? Another שיטה shittah
who is דורכן פחות פחות מכביצה.
dorchan pachot pachot mikabeitzah. That was his other teaching. That was when
it was, that was when the whole thing wasn't sanctified yet. I'm
sorry, wait.
So those ענבים anavim that you were talking about these are תרומה
ענבים?
truma anavim? These are תרומה ענבים. truma anavim. That was
כחולין ענבים. kehulin anavim. Okay? Alright. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like
this, אבל הני דבעי כלי בפה לא עבדו רבנן מעלה. aval hani
deba'ei kli bepeh lo avdu rabanan ma'ala. Okay, so now what, fine.
So we don't know yet the answer to that about if it's
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash things and it's only been oral קדושה, kdusha,
do you still have this restriction that you can't use these tricks?
But I want to just read two more lines to finish with
the pressing of the grapes, because this is ultimately how it tied
in and we'll end with that today. So we read two more
lines. So the גמרא says, דרכן ואפילו טובא? dorchan ve'afilu tuva? One
minute, I don't get how you can be pressing these grapes and
not and the stuff doesn't become טמא. I understand that when רבי
יוחנן said you do less than a כביצה, kabeitzah, but here it
just said you press them. It didn't say less than a כביצה.
kabeitzah. So how did you press these grapes without it becoming טמא?
ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי? Umi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi? Did he
really say that? ואמר רבי יוחנן ענבים שנטמאו, Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan anavim
shenitme'u, and this is the tie-in, when grapes become טמא, yes, you
can get the juice out the following way, if you do דורכן
פחות פחות מכביצה, dorchan pachot pachot mikabeitzah, if you do less than
a כביצה. kabeitzah. So this is the whole reason we had today's
discussion was to tie it into this statement. That here we have
רבי יוחנן saying press grapes and you can use them and whatever
and they're okay, which seemed like what he said yesterday, but here
he did not limit it to the כביצה kabeitzah case, so what's
going on? So the גמרא says, איבעית אימא הכי נמי פחות פחות
מכביצה. Ibayit eima hacha nami pachot pachot mikabeitzah. Simplest answer, you're right.
When he says here press them, he means according to the way
we discussed yesterday, less than a
כביצה. kabeitzah. ואיבעית אימא, Ve'ibayit eima, and if you want, התם דנגעו
להו ברישון דהוו להו אינהו שני, הכא דנגעו בשני דהוו להו שלישי.
hatam denagu lehu berishon dehavu lehu inhu sheni, hacha denagu besheni dehavu
lehu shelishi. So you know what, unfortunately I don't feel it's fair
to you to try to explain that since we're already four minutes
overtime, so... So we will find out tomorrow another way in which
you can press these grapes without the juice becoming טמא even if
you don't do פחות מכביצה. pachos mi-k'beitza. All right.
I so much I so thought